dating is good
yeah dating is good dating is good it's
um
so i don't know if you've been following
melbourne but we're in curfew here
we have been for the last four weeks
yeah so we can leave the house between
uh 5 a.m and 8 p.m and go no more than
five kilometers away
for one hour a day one person shopping
at a time
good heavens for how long one hour
and how long have you been on curfew
four weeks
that's interesting yeah it's it's it's
been interesting
you know bring up dating and i think
well we
what you see behind me that's been date
space for basically the whole year
yeah wow that's pretty intense yeah
yeah interesting i mean yeah it's um
there's something about um
especially especially when taking all
that
we could talk about together and then
condensing that into an hour
from a place where it's like oh yeah i'm
actually under curfew right now i mean
i'm gonna be here the whole time
basically just doing this
but to condense and sort of pull through
you know
um that right place
of well it's something like
well what is it when two minds
come together to
do something of value this seems to be
this seems to be core well i what i see
is i see my daughter
um playing with that do you wanna are we
recording yeah we are good
um i see my daughter playing with that
toy that many kids have which has um
blocks of different shapes and holes of
different shapes
and of course the task is to figure out
how to fit the right block in the right
shaped hole
um and then i actually am now seeing
even the specific
how do you call it development of
capacitor development of skillfulness
where she can pick up the box you can
look at it she can rotate it
grasp which one it is map it to
something in here that tells her what
hole it goes into and then put it in the
hole like no experiments at all
and that's actually i think a really
good metaphor
now we've got some number of blocks that
we're dealing with
um it's larger than four um and we've
got some number of holes we're dealing
with
and the the task is to figure out how
rapidly can we take the complex space of
possibility that is the union of our two
specific complex spaces of possibility
and
collapse it down to the moment that is
the highest
quality event that this particular
movement calls for
and that's i think uh in this
conversation but also i would say in
general like this is a very high
thing for us to be getting better and
better at doing yeah
yeah absolutely yeah
so when i messaged you i did say that
speaking about civilian could be a good
idea
sure it's very ripe yeah um it provides
a
beautiful basis i think to begin to pull
in other things
and perhaps when ultimately lay the
blocks down
in the correct order um i think that's
pretty much what it's about
in the knowledge that those blocks are
to be replaced
appropriately as well so
it seems like it would be a good thing
to you know ask you to introduce the
notion of sivium
to the kind of interested party that
might not have heard you discuss it
before but it's distinctly aware that
we need to build differently things are
changing
and uh it's the kind of person that
likes to consider themselves
well i'm ready for change you know and
i'm willing to and actually i have
the means to participate in some form
um i'm willing to put in the time to
understand
i'm interested in coming into quality
interaction interesting to participate
in that please so
the way i i think i maybe will begin is
something like
at the level of design um
perhaps even just a bit of a critique so
we've endeavored we meaning humanity
have endeavored of course many times to
reinvent the way that we
congregate with we live together um
and in the past several centuries have
done so in ways that are endeavoring to
to do it in a way that is i would say
conscious or intentional right
thoughtful as opposed to merely
functional which is been the was the
order of the day for a long period of
time
and what i would say is different about
the notion of civilian
is that the the design intent came from
the very beginning
with a proposition that uh the problem
that we're trying to to deal with
is let me just begin by saying rather
deep
um and it's maybe the problem of
civilization itself
so we're not just trying to figure out
how to create sort of a nice place to
live
for example or even a place that is
ecologically sound
because there's a uh an awareness of the
implications and complications of
the total set of things that we do under
the heading of civilization
that need to be considered and that the
uh you know the the the effort or the
best intentions
um will tend to be unraveled or
uh will fail or sometimes even create
negative consequences
in a very micro case if you don't
actually think about the global case as
well
so that's maybe in the very beginning is
there a way to put your arms around it
where the the strength of your design is
adequate to something that actually
shifts the underlying basis
of the the deeper problem which i'll
just call the problem of civilization
another language i would call the
problem of gay may
[Music]
and therefore is at least in principle
able able to address that set of
problems
effectively and create something which
is enduring
now it's really interesting that in the
past six months i've been exposed to the
work of one of your uh
somebody who lives near you i think
actually tyson yonkoporta
because he coming from a rather
different direction
ended up coming to some very similar
conclusions and i might be using some of
his ideas
um so the first is the proposition that
in fact
in many ways the problem of civilization
is also the problem of city
that it may in fact be appropriate to
say that all civilizations
are merely the sort of actuation
adjunct of cities so whether you're
talking about roman empire
or you're talking about the british
empire or talking about the american
empire
um or i suppose you can go backwards and
talk about the city-states of greece
in each case the extended territory
as significant as it was may in fact be
properly seen
as being something like the circulatory
system um
of the city which was at the the essence
of it
and in the network of cities by the way
and this is based from my point of view
largely in the work of uh
jeffrey west and louis betancourt which
popularized in the book scale
so that's a very very interesting notion
um
and the next question would be okay why
and more specifically what kinds of
changes would be the adequate changes
to shift that and here again
uh tyson i think is the nail in the head
when he makes a distinction
between what he calls growth and
increase
so here the notion is that
again western betancourt they noticed
that cities have a unique
scaling characteristic which is to say
that as a city grows
certain metrics like say for example
wealth per capita
grow in a very unusual way generally
speaking in nature what we see
is that when an organism and that might
include say like an ecosystem like a
forest or a
a part of what we might consider an
organism like a cell as
as the as the organism grows uh
most of the relevant characteristics um
grow on what's called a a
sublinear scaling so what this means is
for example if i take a
a mouse and i look at the the rate of
metabolism
per unit mass meaning how much energy is
cycling through the organism
uh for the total mass in grams
if i increase the mass the actual
metabolism only increases
at about 85 percent so if i double the
mass
instead of the metabolism doubling it
only increases by 85 percent
which is to say that there's a certain
efficiency
built in and also certain limitations to
scale built in to biological organisms
and this is common across all living
organisms and in fact in common across
human organisms as well like
corporations have a similar scaling
factor if i double the number of
employees in a company
i actually don't double the uh revenue
per employee i actually
tend to it tends to increase i'm sorry
decrease per employee
but cities behave differently
bettencourt and
west discovered that they actually
increased super linear which is to say
if i double the size of the city
and by the way in some sense hold
everything else constant
i will actually get a uh 115
increase of the wealth per capita
or income per capita if you prefer
now that's actually a super super
powerful discovery
um and one of the characteristics so now
i'm kind of going off on my own
um uh what's that called i'm walking my
own plank now
so what what i would propose is that
this
creates that makes the city a certain
kind of a growth attractor
what the city has been trying to do
throughout history since we discovered
the construct of the city has been to
grow
to put as many people as possible in the
city as it can get
um and sort of every problem context
of cities and therefore every problem
context of civilizations that are
attached to them
has to do with the constraints on that
ability
so for example if i put uh say a million
people in a city
i have to feed a million people and if
the only way that i can feed people is
by
hauling uh wheat in on people's
shoulders and bags
i can't pull that off very easily that's
hard to do more or less impossible
so i have to do things like invent roads
or invent barges
right so there's a ratio a relationship
between on the one hand
the physical constraints that are
associated with squeezing human bodies
into
physical space in terms of largely
energy coming in and waste going out
but also what they need to do other
things like meet other people and move
around in the space transportation and
whatnot
the technological capacity of the
environment that we're in
um and then the the limitations to scale
that are are possible right so
effectively every city is is trying to
to solve that problem
and what again what western bettencourt
found was that there was a
a moment where the city would tend to
grow
up to the limits of the existing
technology but remember because
as cities grow the actual certain
characteristics
increase super linearly well one of
those in those characteristics is
actually innovation
so as the cities would grow in uh
population
the innovation of that particular city
and therefore that civilization would
actually tend to also go
super linearly so you'd get these
explosions of innovation which would
tend to cluster around constraints to
growth
and so you would tend to get these step
functions where they'd actually pulse
and then of course you'd get things that
were much much larger
than had previously existed in the world
um
around them you know like the the first
cities you know er and
and a cod and places like that until
eventually they do peter out
and something happens which limits their
capacity to grow whoops i lost you are
we
okay yeah keep going i'm here
so this this this um
this sort of mammon desire to
to grow at all costs and the
kind of the imperial organization of all
space
and to some extent all time as a
subsidiary function to feed the growth
of the city
is a really interesting way of thinking
about what's the problem of civilization
you know everything ultimately becomes a
feed stock
every small town exists largely as a
consequence of its context
in the relationship to the capacity of
it to serve as a way of feeding the
growth of the
of the city all the way up the chain to
the largest cities and ultimately i
guess megalopolises and conservations
that
are now dominate our landscape okay
so then and then what tyson does is he
he presents an alternative
and and he specifically presents an
alternative that was real
in the context of the uh indigenous
uh human groups which he calls
increase and i i love his metaphor
actually he says okay
if i want to increase or or
improve let's just go with a very simple
metric iq
in a human broadly speaking there's two
things i might do
i could grow the number of neurons i
could just make it a larger brain it
could take a brain that weighs
10 kilograms indicator brain that weighs
15 kilograms
or i could increase the quality
of the brain i could increase the not
just the number of
of neural connections uh the synapses
inside but also the quality which ones
specifically are networking with which
ones right the network
topology um and
what i love about that metaphor is that
it's real right human beings actually
ran into a limit
on how rapidly or how big we could get
our brains because of the
the birth canal and so we ran into that
limit
we were evolution was forced to find a
way to continue to increase our
our cognitive capacities by virtue of
increase meaning uh
if you think about development these
processes of development the brain will
actually create a huge number of
connections
then prune the hell of them and then you
know increase again all focusing on not
more neurons but on better connections
okay well that's nice that that's a move
right so the move is to say okay we need
to find a way to move away from
growth as a mandate and move towards
increases of mandate
so that's one key premise of sibium
right first creep premise is we need to
find a way to move away from the city
and all the characteristics that make
the city the city
uh and the second is all right one of
those characteristics is this uh notion
of growth and the
the thing that is the right thing is
increase quality quality of
relationships
specifically and you can think about
that quite practically
and if i'm moving into a city from a
small town
and moving into a city of say a million
people how big is melbourne
i think about three million ish give or
take a million
so i'm moving from a town of about a
hundred a small city of 150
000 and i moved to melbourne part of the
point part of the attraction
is there's just a much larger potential
of relationships there's the likelihood
that i will be able to find people who
are
um high quality relationships for me
they have similar tastes or
interests or whatever is just a lot
larger
by this case two orders of magnitude um
okay that's true but it also has real
problem which is well there's three
million people and the reality
is you're only ever going to meet a
small fraction of them
and only ever going to be in
relationship with an even smaller
fraction
so beyond a certain small number which
is around 150 000 people or so
um the bigger problem is actually search
it's not
math right you don't actually need to
think about like the internet
the internet is vast i don't need to
have a bigger internet what i need to
have is a better way of finding the one
the aspects of the internet that are
relevant to me and by the way now
so that's another piece right we start
thinking about increase or something
about quality
we start thinking about oh okay well the
move is to say
how do i move away from just adding more
nodes to the graph
and move towards getting better and
better and better at finding
the right relationships okay when i look
at the right relationships it seems
there's three primary characteristics
one is who
so that's the easiest like right now who
should i be talking to you right now or
should i be talking to someone else
the second is what right as we began the
conversation there's a very large number
of possible things that we could
have in our relationship and being able
to orient on that what quickly
and well is a is a thing and then in
some sense how
and how largely has to do with the
skillfulness
on both of our parts to enter into
relationship how
deeply fully uh how intimately um
how sustainably how resiliently how
anti-fragile can we actually make the
relationship itself
um in some sense that's that
all right so then let me make another
move
and i think that's probably well i'll
stop for a moment
i'm gonna break that promise i've got
things are pouring in from the back of
my head right now
so the next move is is an insight that i
had recently
and i think it's right so i'll put it
out there i've already put it in a video
but i'll put it here as well
one of the things that has been
constraining the possibility
of cyvium up until very recently
is the the obligate
binding of the virtual with the physical
so when i look at that that super linear
scaling
and i look at it very closely this
notion of trying to squeeze as many
bodies into the same space as possible
what i notice is that the thing that's
really
looking to be connected is not bodies
it's minds the real thing that is
actually driving
growth is minds more minds metcap's law
specifically
it's communication is the governing
protocol and the reason why cities are
cities is because up until very recently
the only way we could communicate was to
be in person
um and even still relatively until like
i guess we had copied
the bandwidth of communication right
interpersonal and body communication
still dwarfed
radically dwarfed the bandwidth of
telecommunication but take the clock
back 250 years and it was
obvious that if you wanted to
communicate with other people you had to
be
in the same room more or less
so if communication between minds is the
thing that wants to
increase necessary wants to grow to all
right it wants to be everyone at least
in potential
um okay i get it and so the city has
been kind of like dragging bodies along
trying to get minds into connection and
having to deal with the fact these minds
are connected to bodies
but nowadays this is no longer i don't
think
a primary constraint as we see in this
call you and i are not in the same room
and yet we're having a conversation
we're communicating
and it's not bad right it's not quite
the same as being in the same room but
it's not bad
and i suspect on the one hand we're
getting better at it because we've been
forced to
by curfew and whatnot and on the other
hand i think we can continue to get
better at it with things like
photorealistic immersive vr for example
creating possibilities of increasing
simulation of embodied experience
i'm going to put a flag there by the way
because that of course can be a terrible
thing
but we're now walking the razor's edge
between terrible things and awesome
things i don't think there's a way for
us to step forward without having
both sides of the razor's edge in every
step
so what we can do now is we can decouple
the virtual from the physical and we can
render into the virtual what is the
virtual
and now of course be liberated to render
into the physical what is physical
and rediscover in the physical what
tyson's been talking about
the the more natural humane human scale
ways of life that are in many ways
indigenous
having really high quality face-to-face
interactions at the dunbar level
with other human beings frankly who we
may spend large amounts of time with
real deep woven communities
and by the way with nature really
descaling the
these massively densified locations that
separate us from nature
and finding ways to live lightly with
nature and i'm going to flag that as
well this is non-trivial well in fact we
want we can double click on it because
it's a
it's an interesting point of contention
to be frank
but then you've got a really powerful
new combo right a situation where
there's a virtual and the virtual
civilian is is everything right so think
of it as the thing beyond facebook and
hopefully radically better i
designed from the very beginning to
actually be healthy
but where everyone all minds at least
all those who choose to be there
can be so it truly is a global community
of minds
and that's it once you've hit that there
is no more to go all minds at least in
principle
have the possibility of being in
connection with each other in a
appropriately designed virtual and then
the flip side
the flip side of the civilian is a a
global mesh work
of halonically nested so different
levels of scale
but but really focused on the lowest
level of scale on the level of
neighborhoods and villages
[Music]
of humans living in a very
humane human scale way and i think i
would sort of add a third piece to that
which is
my experience and i think there's good
reason to believe this is a general
experience is that the
the projecting of self projecting of
mind into the virtual
is quite taxing you know a conversation
of an hour
in person particularly a conversation of
an hour in person say in the forest
right surrounded by nature um has a
certain level of
cost for me i'm introverted uh i think
extroverts enjoy it
i mean i don't i um
yeah i hear you i mean i definitely hear
you on the increased cost
i think it has a lot to do with audience
and the the digital is definitely a
thing
um but i'm sure you've had experiences
as well of speaking on stage perhaps or
speaking to a crowd where
let's say your voice wasn't that well
received as being something which was
quite taxing as well you know at least
yeah
i agree with you and there's something
there's like three elements to oh that
that conversation or sorry that that
experience
um to be frank makes me move to a tool
kit that describes things like fields of
energy
yeah um and i've had experiences where
i actually feel the energy of the group
increasing my energy on stage but then
when i get off stage i feel like i got
unplugged from a light socket and i'm
wrung out
i've had experiences where it's been
kind of a fight
and there's been uh and that also is
quite draining
i've had a few experiences but they're
quite rare where what you might say
the i sort of the spiritual or
psychological psychosocial practices of
the group
are actually highly nutritive and so you
walk away from the conversation with the
group actually feeling
refreshed yeah um this is harder to do
in the digital but that's the point
so what i would point to is something
like um
new shamanic practices new psycho
technologies
um that bring into the nature of the
virtual
with some thoughtfulness so that we are
not depleted or not unduly depleted
by our interactions in the virtual and
also can take advantage of
the way that we can recharge ourselves
so much more effectively
when the physical is really designed to
be nurturing
uh yeah yeah i hear you
okay okay so that's that's one big run
there's another big run that we can do
if you'd like that speaks more to this
if you just deserve it from a different
angle but that's
that's a good bite for now i suppose
yeah well i mean i certainly would like
you know i am also conscious of time um
so let me see if i can provide a couple
things back here
um because man there's a few different
roads to go on here
a few different tributaries
so you know i'm hearing a lot and what
i'm here what i'm hearing is really good
you know i think i'm i think i'm with
you um
if i can put things into slightly
different language
seems like and it's going to be a bit
abs like quite
abstract to begin with but it seems like
there's a value to be found in
gathering around or near the center
right that the center matters to the
periphery if we take like the heart
right there's
blood moving all around the body it's
got to come back to it
i hear you when it comes uh you know an
analysis of city as
being historically at least this
movement of bringing minds together in
relation
as enabling increased wealth and
innovation
by this percentage increase coming of
course at the expense of just broadly
the infrastructure that enables
whatever is around the center to in fact
be nourished by what is in fact the
whole
you know um so good
i mean i did have a chat with a friend a
little while ago his name's kieran
and he spoke to me about how you know
his understanding of why cities came
into being as they did had to do with um
protecting in physical space space a
store of value
right the store of banks fundamentally
now i don't think that needs um
challenge the notion of what we're
speaking about
i think we can see it as complementary
right if we're protecting something of
value around the center whatever that
thing is there needs to be a quite a
precise
um formation of relationality enabling
of at least enough stability
for the center to hold around that store
of value whatever it is or that
conception or sense of value well we can
we can specifically point to the notion
of stock or the notion of store of value
um there's a there's a sort of a
perturbation at the origin point of city
that one of the pieces is the separation
of of the human in complex flows
in cycles into something that begins the
process of extraction
and extraction is the movement that
comes before store
i mean you can't store anything of value
until you've first extracted that value
and so it's um you know there's a cycle
there's a there's a separation there's
extraction
there's store then of course in the
context of store there's a number of
different things that happen
including protect yep yep
yep and um well it seems like unless
we're
breathing that value back and forth such
that it is not extraction
but a right reciprocal relationship we
are
that seems to be how it goes um although
we kind of fool ourselves because we
don't live very long and sometimes it
takes a while to be
that's right it can look real good it's
the short term
planning for the short term if the short
term is several hundred years
unfortunately can be quite seductive to
humans yeah it feels like the long term
if you're planning if
your own personal planning horizon is
shorter yeah
and that you know i think it's worse
it's worth highlighting this as well
that i think the
the buy-in which is probably the wrong
terminology to
really grok and take seriously this
whole domain of conversation
requires like honestly
and with deep humility
like really deep humility because it's
not only it's not it's not an easy task
seeking to solve for where solve is not
the final solution but is in some sense
the right next step of relating to these
grand problems
of living together in such a way that
endures
in a way that we've never done before in
a way that is so drastically beyond what
the lifespan
of or in a way that opens itself to
enabling
so many more lifespans than just that of
the individual and is of course
not only about human beings but the
entire ecology
as it has to be otherwise you're not
taking seriously this um
notion of breathing in and out this
reciprocal exchange of
of value um it just doesn't seem to work
like that right i was watching a
documentary about um mushrooms
which was quite wonderful fantastic
fungi i think it was called
um i've seen that yeah i mean i just
thoroughly recommend everyone check it
out for just a visceral
hit of um nature presenting
so many of the um the right patterns
so it comes to me to say that is a a
trade
and i think it's a very good trade and
and to use verveiki's language because
he does such a great job of
making it precise it's a trait of
relevance for salience
um
[Music]
you know the extractive life
at the end of the day is actually a
salience life
salience here in some sense representing
the
the like cotton candy is super salient
it tastes really sweet
and if you lack a discerning tongue
you may think that it's super good and
therefore attractive
and will choose to eat cotton candy over
well i guess the archetype is broccoli
and
if you have a short enough time horizon
which in this case is usually about 45
seconds
um that might feel like a good trade but
if you're able to
metabolize or feel the consequence of oh
wait now i feel terrible
i feel sick and by the way i only eat
about three bites of this giant pile of
cotton candy
they begin to realize that it's actually
a bad trade but but the proposal i'd
like to make
is um it's not broccoli we're talking
about
it's meaningfulness even the sacred
and i think that's the trade the trade
is the trade of
the the merely salient
what is in fact ultimately the
superficial
um for the truly
meaningful which is to say the sacred
and i think in this most profane age
that might be a trade that people can
grasp
um easily which is to say that once
you've felt that
trade once you've actually noticed that
it is possible to live life moment to
moment in contact with the sacred and
what that actually means and feels like
then that actually becomes a nice
short-term
trade and you can just look at the thing
on the left hand and thing on the right
hand and choose the thing in the right
hand you don't actually have to
try to trade your short term success for
something which is kind of an imaginary
long term
you can trade your immediate relevance
your immediate sacred your immediate
meaningfulness fulfillment and
well-being
for your immediate superficial
your immediate super salient
i think that's a nice trade i think
that's one that is plausible
and i would actually by the way say that
that weaves into the second
line of uh of the civilian story
that trade that shift um
consciously done and deliberately done
which is to say uh
what i just said we can actually look at
it and think about it and get a sense
at the level of things like cognitive
science what we're talking about here
with some precision uh and then say okay
okay that makes sense
my heart and my mind can both say yes to
this
yeah yeah the good flow
the good flow i've taken to
i like that expression just in my own
kind of a kind of
a lower resolution way in but you know
it's the um
well maybe maybe like this might take us
a while to get back to the completion of
that thought but
we don't have all the time in the world
you know
um you speak about the value in linking
minds together
and a few moments later we're speaking
about sacredness
and we're speaking about a right
relationality of heart and mind
which is in fact the kind of
so perhaps it's worth
just for clarity's sake um
speaking to these notions a little bit
more um
it doesn't seem to me there can be minds
in relationship
with each other absent i mean for a very
long span of time
perhaps at all absent right
relationality of bodies being in
together
that might not mean we're necessarily
right next to each other
right but i'm doing something with mine
over here um
sitting comfortably on a chair at least
for now
and the mechanism which is not the right
way of speaking about but the link
between
us like why why we care about this at
all like what what is it
we're caring and moving with right what
is the flow that we can be part of
is not exactly just a flow of mind
right it's a flow of something else it's
a flow of something
that is constitutive of
webbing knitting together is the
being together of yeah nice
um so can i see back to what i'm hearing
i think it's quite beautiful i like it a
lot it'll take me i think a while to
metabolize it completely but the
i mean in some sense the premise of what
you're saying is hey look
this thing that we've been calling
communication and perhaps
communications channel and
body are kind of the same thing
so if i am speaking to you in person
across a range of four or five seven
feet um i happen to be using air
as the medium but my body is connecting
to your body
there's a touch there has to be there
has to be actual contact
and if i'm speaking to you across i
guess this is probably about 3 000 miles
um pulling light into a camera throwing
the camera into a computer throwing the
computer up into a satellite zipping it
about and coming
back down i'm still touching you the
difference between the two is in some
sense non-existent
our bodies are in relationship directly
we are
as as good as dancing
that's that's powerful i think that's
right actually that's very well put
um and this speaks to i think the hmm
well i don't know that it's gonna take
me a while to integrate that
well i think it means speaks in part to
the
um the gradualness of this process
of um coming into right relationship
with
the whos with who
i'll say some more things about that but
it's like
feeling what the right touch
is in this new channel in this new
medium it's a
it's a very it's a very interesting
thing i mean
how much of our interaction is mediated
here by the voice and listening how much
is mediated by
what i've been able to learn about body
language that you can see given this
percentage of my body right i mean
certainly some
um so how much are we sort of
bootstrapping on
what we've learned in traditional
physical space that we're porting over
here versus what is
possible in terms of efficiency of
interaction
and integrity and integrity of
communication precisely within this
channel itself
i mean these are also things in
development
um and it's experiments with this kind
of thing like i thought about perhaps um
not for this conversation in particular
because it'd be almost too radical be
almost too radical
for me to be sitting down in that couch
with like the
the camera presented a certain way just
like
you know cross-legged like
really relaxed back like i would be if
we were talking here you know i'd be
like hey jordan do you want to sit down
right and i'd be
i'd be lounging a bit but i'm not
lounging here i'm i'm forward right and
that's respectful
you know i was talking with my with with
tassie my girlfriend about this you know
it's respectful i mean i'm here i'm i'm
ready
and we're doing something here i want to
create something beautiful with you
and i respect you and so here i am and
yet
this is taxing because i'm in my living
room and i usually
lounge over there that's a lounge right
so there's
so many so many of these signals um
and um so maybe we could port this
over to um something that i do i do
think about quite a bit and i think
about
when it comes to the question of
what is it appropriate to record i.e
kind of like when we
speak about such things as sacredness
the very thing which we should be most
careful about
boxing up and pointing to and saying
that is the thing right there and
forgetting ourselves always in
relationship with it
as the kind of constitutive
generators of it along with everything
else in relationship
right um we
we come up we come upon something and
it's like
oh we want to
it's it's it's uh it's it's water it's
water through a net and
so recording something is is we have to
be careful about it but then
okay i want to link this to something
else um
and it's the notion of hierarchy um and
the notion of hetaraki and also one of
the
sort of um characteristics of
game b um
so game b as i've heard you described
with jim
on a few occasions is characterized or
aims at a kind of meta stability
broadly speaking to my understanding a
kind of endurance
and a kind of anti-fragility or at least
resilience to perturbations
and change enabling of continuity of
relationship and
development um
[Music]
network centric or network oriented
network centric is that what you say is
one of the other
characterizations that was an older
formulation but yeah
right okay okay um and another one is um
non-hierarchical
am i right with that yeah
so so this is kind of interesting just
to add to that it's it's not um how do i
say it like
ideologically extinguish the notion of
hierarchy but rather um specifically
about shifting the hierarchical
to be of service there's a whole lot of
this like
basically the unseating of something and
moving into his proper
location relationship in many cases the
primary problems we're dealing with in
game a is you know the tools becoming
the masters
or addiction we've become dependent upon
our tools and have forgotten
in many ways that they were tools in the
first place and have taken them as
as obligate um so an unseating of that
and
repositioning things into right
relationship is a big part of it so
good okay yeah good i mean that
resonates very strongly
um it's uh
perhaps not the clearest it's perhaps
not the clearest to say non-hierarchical
at least in terms of how it hits me
because it's yeah it's definitely not
people think it is meaning
anarchic or flat right yeah non the word
non negates hierarchical
um so to complete so to complete then
what i'm seeing at least the the kind of
the right way to hold a notion of
hierarchy and
i'd love some feedback on this i will
try to see it more clearly is
something like more of a wave where you
have natural peaks
that give way to something
more flat um and then to re reestablish
again
um and that the the peaks hierarchical
peaks would be something like
um like it's again staying in a kind of
metaphor space but i kind of um
or one way to think about them this is
not the only way
certainly certainly not but it's a kind
of ceremony
where wisdom
learning is actually conferred
so that all reach
that point um and so when and so
i started off by talking about recording
and i don't think i would be so um
so mix and match here if we had a bit
longer to speak
but there's something about um
there's something about the creation of
artifacts and ceremony
there's something about events and
ceremony
which seems deeply
important um
this relationship between process and
event alexander bartow is speaking about
this relationship between process
and event been obviously very interested
in process
um and we're always engaging in events
but it's the kind of
it's it's it's a feeling of a feeling
into
an orchestration a kind of um
as a summoning you've spoken about mesh
works
how is it that the waves then all of a
sudden peak like what are we gathering
around
bringing back in this notion of of
center like what are we gathering around
good yeah the notion of censor i think
is exactly the place to go um oh
okay so let's just maybe invoke the
notion of coherence
and the notion of center um
i'm not sure if values and purposes come
in but
let's see if there's a there's a there's
a proper center
and by prop what i mean is something
like
there's a a distinct and high integrity
shared sense of the what and the why
in the context of some given event
very concrete uh the the church is on
fire
in our our town village okay well that's
the center
our collective intention there needs to
be no uh top-down
pushing and there's no formal structure
our collective heads pivot in that
direction our collective heart rates
increase our collective eyes
dilate and then we begin the process
in a space of coherence meaning each and
every
are simultaneously oriented towards the
same center
something must be done so this is very
delicious in right now
it's not clear exactly what but what
must be done the how
is quite unknown but the the what and
the yr
we need to put out the fire we need to
save the church and the y is unspoken
it's a value right the values
are held in uh in common there's a
common
orientation a common basis of values
um so then we begin to shift from values
to purposes
in the context of purposes there is a
there's a right
it's as simple as that there's a sort of
a natural i used to talk about with
schmacktenberger as a natural hierarchy
and there are there are some who are
properly the most
capable of organizing people into the
right kind of structure to be able to
address the problem at hand
um it's unwise to put the
two-year-olds in charge of of of
managing the
the bucket brigade it is wise to put the
ones who are stronger
to carry the heavier water i mean it's
not complicated if you sort of just deal
with it
though if you were calling it the bucket
brigade i think you might actually
that might be the toddler version to be
honest the church is burning let's get
the bucket brigade
not a lot of water is going to make it
to the fire i'm afraid
having a two-year-old and lots of
buckets and lots of spilled water
but i think that's the key right once
you have a proper center
uh once there's been something where the
the
values have oriented a a group of
individuals
into it is in fact a coherent whole
around
a what is now a shared purpose
then the right structure is just part of
reality and the mighty structure might
be anything it's hard to know exactly
and part of the real skillfulness is to
orient ourselves into that right
structure
but oftentimes it will have a division
of labor and that division of labor
often will have
different people taking different
responsibilities and in many cases there
will be a hierarchy because certain
people will either be more skilled
naturally or more skilled experientially
and therefore it is appropriate for them
to have more responsibility in the
context of the nature of the
purpose that is part of the shared
the shared group one of the problems
that i think we run into in our current
context is that we don't have coherent
groups
you know so we take what are effectively
random strangers with quite distinct
values
um and no shared purpose and we force
them
to do stuff together we force them to
coordinate and we create these weird
truncating governance things like
like democracy where we it's kind of it
is very much taking that peg
it is nothing more or less than forcing
round pegs into square
holes and it's because of the
the means and modalities of cosmopolitan
cities
have required the forcing together and
the admixture
of people into spaces that don't have
the time
or the space to find their coherence
and therefore has required that we build
tools of
coordination tools of forcing random
groups of people into being at least
somewhat effective
and then imposing what then becomes
formal hierarchy on the basis of that
effective randomness
and therein lies the problem right so we
might say that's another
distinction in the difference between
city and sivium is uh
this notion of proceeding from coherent
holes
on the basis of some sort of shared
values that then have
a a proper center
as a whole and then from that place the
their their movement into
how is um
more problem of competence than it is a
problem of of of process
formal process the process is organic
um there's that now you write up the
other one
how did it work well what i was seeing
there was i was seeing my friend zach
stein
and his emphasis on teacherly authority
or on education
and it's funny because if you wanted to
make fun of him he could notice that
he's sort of
it's easy to know that if he's sitting
in a group where he's going to bring
into the conversation
the word education will definitely come
up um but
this is because it's a mess now and also
is universally applicable
at all times every relationship always
has
a educational content right that's how
we do things we're not just doing
something we're also growing our
capacity
in every everything we do and that
creates a nice
i think um how do i say it
signpost or orientation on what this
sense of coherence and the sense of um
proper center maybe feel like
you know if there's a the right
relationship of the
process if looked at to the lens of
education which is from my point of view
the same as the lens of
roughly the same as parenting
is you'll feel it and if you feel the
flow
of education is there and ideally
maximally there really is a sense of oh
i am growing as much as i can in the
context of this encounter i'm not just
doing i am growing
um that actually is a really good way of
knowing whether or not you're in the
right
relationship
yeah yeah absolutely
well um i'd say we have about
a minute more yeah which is uh sad but i
guess it is what it is
yeah it is what it is um there's so much
more to talk about
yeah to be to be honest with you i think
that
i think that around about three hours
three and a half hours
possibly feels right for me to
um get where it's possible to go
in a way that would be very meaningful
and i think deeply valuable there's
there's um there's something about
pacing
you know forrest speaks about the
question of when as being a question of
mysticism
the pacing of these interactions um
i i feel like in in some ways i
you know playfully i didn't violate
anything
but i i jumped at grabbing a few things
to bring into the
the pot too too quickly and i could only
really do that with you in this context
because i know you can kind of go
all right yeah i was really throwing
paint at the wall in some respects
but you know we can more gently you know
make those brush strokes
why don't we just make a commitment to
having two and a half more conversations
okay okay okay we can do that
um although the half might be
challenging but this was good
i think um what we're gonna do so we'll
split it right down the middle so
instead of doing it this way we'll do it
this way
yeah yeah good well i think you know i
think there's um
you know in the first little bit there
um a nice introduction to civilian
and for those people who are listening
to this there are
you know breadcrumbs to follow for ways
to
be involved in conversation now um
that's something that
you know i'm facilitating with other
people through this conversation and
these kind of
mutual learning environments which nora
bateson speaks about but
um you know the this isn't something
that um
you have to uh put down and then be in
complete
discontinuity with there is real
opportunity
it's just people here that are open to
having conversations so
so yeah look at the description and all
the rest of it and if you're interested
it's possible to speak so yeah all right
jordan well
it's good to see you um good to see you
i hope you're very well hopefully um
curfew wears itself out and you're able
to go back
outside and congregate good heavens
yeah yeah well i've been doing my best
online
um
yeah the journey continues that's for
sure
all right bye-bye